Chicago & Northwestern Transportation Company Records 5533
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Series III: Minneapolis and St. Louis Railway Motive Power and Operations Data, 1930-1949
  - Carriers' Conference Committee Forms D-49-7. Use of Diesel Locomotives. Completed., 1949 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Carriers' Conference Committee Forms D-49-9. Stream Locomotives. Completed., 1949 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Carriers' Conference Committee Forms D-49-21. Operating Rule Failures or Infractions for 1944-1948. Completed., 1949 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Carriers' Conference Committee Forms D-49-27. Diesel Locomotive for 1946-1948. Completed., 1949 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Monthly Report of Railway Accidents., 1947 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    To the Bureau of Transport Economics and Statistics, Interstate Commerce Commission. September 1947. For the M&St.L Rwy.
  - Association of Western Railways. Form 6-A. Trips Made By Division., 1930 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    August 10-16, 1930. Minneapolis and St. Louis Railway Company.
  - Association of Western Railways. Form 6-A. Trips Made by Passenger Trains., 1930 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Association of Western Railways. Form 6-A. Trips Made by Through Passenger Trains., 1930 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Association of Western Railways. Form 6-A. Trips Made by Through Freight Trains, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Association of Western Railways. Form 6-A. Trips Made by Local Freight Trains., 1930 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Association of Western Railways. Form 6-A. Trips Made by Other Road Service Trains., 1930 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Series IV: Dispute between the Minneapolis and St. Louis Railway and the Federated Shop Crafts, 1920-1953
  This series contains records documenting a dispute between the M&St.L and its employees who worked in non-operating crafts. These employees belonged to the International Association of Machinists; the International Brotherhood of Boilermakers, Iron Ship Builders, and Helpers of America; the International Brotherhood of Blacksmiths, Drop Forgers and Helpers; the Amalgamated Sheet Metal Workers International Alliance; International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers; and the Brotherhood of Railway Carmen of America. This series includes documentation on who represented the non-operating employees, including a decision by the U.S. Railroad Labor Board regarding the representation, and the Constitution and By-Laws of the M&St.L Railroad System Association, Federated Shop Crafts AFL, which was deemed the representative organization instead of the American Federation of Railroad Workers. The complete filing of the 1921 case, including a transcript of the testimony before the U.S. Railroad Labor Board, is found in this series.
  Of particular interest is the documentation of the Great Railroad Strike of 1922, also called the Shopmen's Strike. This strike, which occurred in July and August 1922, was a nationwide strike launched by seven of the sixteen railroad labor organizations in existence of the time and the largest railroad work stoppage since the Pullman Strike of 1894. This series contains records of the financial losses suffered by the M&St.L as well as a timeline of strike activities that occurred on their properties.
  Reports on conferences and Agreements between the M&St.L and the Federated Shop Crafts are also located in this series. Also found are changes to the agreement with regards to the seniority rights of employees who served in the military during the course of their employment.
  - Memorandum of Agreement Covering Mechanics' Seniority After Military Service., 1945-1953 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Association of Western Railways Circular Nos. 246 in re Advancement of apprentices, etc. to position of Mechanic. Agreement is between Minneapolis and St. Louis Railway Company and Federated Shop Crafts, Railway Employees Dept., AFL.
  - Disputes and Mediations between Minneapolis and St. Louis Railway Company and Federated Shop Crafts, Docket No 4047. [Folder 1 of 2], 1920- 1934 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Includes correspondence; filings; transcript of proceedings before U.S. Labor Board, Docket 979, held December 5, 1921; and the Constitution and By-Laws of the Minneapolis and St. Louis System Association, adopted September 2, 1922
  - Disputes and Mediations between Minneapolis and St. Louis Railway Company and Federated Shop Crafts, Docket No 4047. [Folder 2 of 2], 1920- 1934 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Includes correspondence; filings with the U.S. Railroad Administration; list of names of members of the System Association Lodge; copy of National Agreement for Shop Crafts; statement of the aggregate cost of the Shop Crafts' Strike of 1922; timeline of events of Shop Crafts' Strike of 1922; and ex parte filings by M&St.L Rwy management with U.S. Railroad Labor Board.
  - Proceedings of the US Railroad Labor Board. Docket No. 4047., 1934 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Federated Shop Crafts, Railway Employees Dept., AFL v. Minneapolis and St. Louis Railway.
- Series V: Employee Manuals, 1941-1968
  This series contains bound volumes with information for railroad employees. The manuals cover different aspects of railroad employment. Some are personnel focused, such as the manuals on interviewing, salary administration, and workforce reductions; the directories of payroll numbers and disability ratings also focus on personnel matters. Instructional matters are also covered, both in the manual on preventing workplace mishaps and in the routing guides, which instruct employees on interchanges with other railroads. Finally, a bound volume containing the proceedings of the American Association of Railroad Superintendents' annual conference is also located in this collection.
  - Provisional Occupational Disability Rating Schedule. U.S. Railroad Retirement Board., 1946 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Payroll Numbers and Area Location Lists, 1961-1966 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    Lists of employees by union affiliation.
  - Mishap Prevention Handbook. Volume 1., 1968 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Interviewers' Manual. Chicago and Northwestern System., 1954 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Report on Workforce Reduction. [Folder 1 of 2], 1965-1968 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Report on Workforce Reduction. [Folder 2 of 2], 1965-1968 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Proceedings of the Sixty-Fifth Annual Meeting and Committee Reports. American Association of Railroad Superintendents., 1961 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    Bound book.
  - Minimum Wage Poster, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    Contains a poster.
  - United Transportation Union Merger. Special Board of Adjustment. Award Nos. 1-17, 20-26, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    Claims and decisions by the Board.
  - Elgin, Joliet and Eastern Salary Administration Manual., 1957 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Wage and Salary Administration (Box 4, Folder 21)
    No date.
  - The Wheeling and Lake Erie Railway Company. Joint Routing Guide. 79-A., 1941 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - The Wheeling and Lake Erie Railway Company. Joint Routing Guide. 79-A., 1942-1952 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Series VI: National Railroad Adjustment Board. Decisions and Awards, 1952-1955
  The National Railroad Adjustment Board [NRAB] was created by 45 U.S. Code 153, part of the Railway Labor Act. It is overseen by the National Mediation Board, which was created by the 1934 amendment to Railway Labor Act to oversee the arbitration of labor disputes in the railway and airline industries. The NRAB is tasked with arbitrating minor disputes, i.e. grievance arbitrations, in the railway industry. This series contains the NRAB's decision in cases that either affected labor relations on the M&St.L system, or cases that directly involved M&St.L personnel. The latter are all cases of employees' claims for wages, filed by the Switchmen's Union of North America [SUNA].
  - National Railroad Adjustment Board. Award No. 1900. Docket No. 1751., 1955 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - National Railroad Adjustment Board. Award No. 1901. Docket No. 1760., 1955 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - National Railroad Adjustment Board. Award No. 1902. Docket No. MC 1526-99 2-WT-I-55, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - National Railroad Adjustment Board. Award No. 1905. Docket 1765 2-MP-CM-55., 1955 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - National Railroad Adjustment Board. Award No. 1906. Docket No. 1771 2-IC-EW-55, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - National Railroad Adjustment Board. Award No. 1907. Docket No. 1773, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    2-PRR-URRWA, CIO-55.
  - National Railroad Adjustment Board. Award No. 1910. Docket 1764., 1955 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    2-CNO and TP-EW-55.
  - National Railroad Adjustment Board. Award No. 1911. Docket No. 1769., 1955 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    2-AT and SF-CM-55.
  - National Railroad Adjustment Board. Award No. 1912. Docket No. 1749., 1955 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    2-UT-EM-55.
  - National Railroad Adjustment Board. Award No. 1913. Docket No. 1775., 1955 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    2-SP(PL)-CM-55
  - National Railroad Adjustment Board. Award No. 17124. Docket No. 30-088., 1955 (Box 5, Folder 53)
    August 4 1955. In re Claim for One Yard Day's Pay. Filing from SUNA.
  - National Railroad Adjustment Board. Award Nos. 17122-17124. Southern Pacific Claim for One Yard Day., 1952-1955 (Box 5, Folder 54)
    In re Claim for One Yard Day's Pay. Includes correspondence and filings from SUNA.
  - National Railroad Adjustment Board. Award No. 17125. Docket No. 30-090., 1952-1955 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    In re Claim for One Yard Day's Pay. Filing from SUNA.
  - National Railroad Adjustment Board. Award No. 17126. H.L. Murphy's Claim for Time and One-Half., 1950-1955 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - National Railroad Adjustment Board. Award No. 17253-17254. Martin Kearney's Claim for Extra Day's Pay., 1952-1955 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    In re Claim for One Yard Day's Pay. Filings from SUNA.
  - National Railroad Adjustment Board. Award No. 17139. R. O'Connor's Claim for Additional Day's Pay., 1951-1955 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - National Railroad Adjustment Board. Award No. 17259. Switchmen's Minimum Yard Day Claim., 1952-1955 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    In re Claim for One Yard Day's Pay. Multiple filings from SUNA.
  - National Railroad Adjustment Board. Award No. 17260. E. Jacobson's Claim for Foreman's Rate Pay, 1952-1955 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Filing by SUNA.
- Series VII: Federal Railroad Legislation and Emergency Boards, 1918-1951
  This series contains records of federal agencies which regulated the railroad industry. This includes the nationalization of the railroads during World War I under the U.S. Railroad Administration and the decision by an Emergency Board in 1942 to ensure that labor disputes did not hinder the U.S.'s war mobilizations during World War II. Also found in this series is the legislation that amended the Railroad Retirement Acts and Railroad Unemployment Insurance Act in 1951.
  - Railroad Retirement Acts and Railroad Unemployment Insurance Act., 1951 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Report to the President by the Emergency Board., 1942 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    July 21, 1942
  - US Railroad Administration Circulars., 1918-1919 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - US Railroad Administration. Supplements to General Order No. 27., 1918-1919 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Series VIII: Carrier Mergers, 1958-1968
  This series contain documentation of various mergers between carriers that occurred during the 1950s and 1960s; this period is sometimes referred to Railroad Merger Era. It began in the late 1950s with the approval of the merger between the Norfolk and Western with The Virginian Railway. The culmination of the railroad merger era was the merger of the Pennsylvania Railroad with the New York Central Railroad in 1968, forming the Penn Central Transportation Company.
  This series contains some of the Agreements of the Penn Central merger, as well as copies of Agreements from other large carrier mergers. These records are present because they were used as templates for the Agreements used in CNW's merger with Chicago Great Western Railway in 1968. The various Consolidation Agreements demonstrate how complicated and unwieldy this process was, and helps demonstrate why the majority of these mergers resulted in larger carrier companies declaring bankruptcy and led to the deregulation of the industry and the creation of national corporations ConRail and Amtrak which operated on what had been the Penn Central's tracks.
  - Merger Protective Agreement and Implementing Agreement No. 1 Between The Great Northern Pacific and Burlington Lines, Inc. and Its Employees Represented by the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers, 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    Consolidation of seniority districts, of terminal services, of terminals through attrition and other means, passenger service, zones, and schedules.
  - Penn Central Merger: Yard Agreement No. 4. Indianapolis, Indiana., 1967 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    Agreement between Pennsylvania Railroad and N.Y. Central with the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers and Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen.
  - Penn Central Merger: Consolidation Agreement, East St. Louis, Terra Haute, and Indianapolis Facilities, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    June 1, 1966. Agreement between Pennsylvania Railroad and N.Y. Central with the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers and Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen.
  - Penn Central Merger: Agreement for Protection of Employees in Merger., 1964-1966 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Penn Central Merger: Road Agreement No. 1. Indianapolis, Indiana., 1966 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    December 1, 1966. Agreement between Pennsylvania Railroad and N.Y. Central with the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers and Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen.
  - Penn Central Merger: Yard Agreement No. 2. East St. Louis, Illinois., 1967 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    January 13, 1967. Agreement between Pennsylvania Railroad and N.Y. Central with the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers and Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen.
  - Burlington Northern Merger: Agreement for Protection of Employees in Merger., 1962 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Chicago Great Western and North Western Railway Merger, Rough Draft, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    Filed with copy of October, 11 1966 Pennsylvania Railroad and New York Central Railroad Agreement.
  - RLEA Meeting re CGW and CNW Merger, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    April 14, 1966.
  - CGW and CNW Merger: ICC Examination Report, Labor Protective Conditions, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    Appendix to Agreement
  - Seaboard and Coast Line Merger: Agreement for Protection of Employers in Merger., 1966 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - BLE-Terminal Consolidation Agreements Governing the Consolidation of the Ft. Wayne and Ohio Terminal Facilities in the Norfolk and Western et al. Merger, 1959-1966 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    Sent to CNW Vice President of Labor Relations T.M. Van Patten at his request
  - BLE-Terminal Consolidation Agreements: Interim Agreement. Toledo, Ohio., 1966 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - CGW and CNW Merger, Rough Draft, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Organizational Charts for railroad companies, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Chicago Great Western and North Western Railway Merger. [Folder 1 of 4], 1968 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    Agreements with BLE, BLF&E, and SUNA.
  - Chicago Great Western and North Western Railway Merger. [Folder 2 of 4], 1968 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    Agreements with BRT and ORC&B.
  - Chicago Great Western and North Western Railway Merger. [Folder 3 of 4], 1968 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    Route Map and Attachments.
  - Chicago Great Western and North Western Railway Merger. [Folder 4 of 4], 1968 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    Attachments.
- Series IX: National Rules Movements, 1940-1960
  This series contains records relating to National Rules Movements. The bulk of the records come from the Rules Movement of 1958, but other years are represented. The National Rules Movement were efforts by the railroad labor organizations to change operating rules for railroad employees. The Rules Movement of 1950 was concerned with moving to a 40-Hour week from a 48-Hour week with no reduction in pay. The 1958 Rules Movement was concerned with the operation of rules establishing time limits for the handling of claims and grievances; hiring practices; safety, health, and sanitation; and, accidents. Other issues addressed in Rules Movements of 1958 include vacation and holiday agreements.
  The records in this series include Section 6 Notices, in which the Unions notify the carriers of their desire to change the language of their Agreements; records of conferences had between the two sides to negotiate changes; and, circulars from carriers' conference informing other member railroads of changes made to Agreements.
  Of interest are records regarding the efforts of the American Railway Supervisors Association to organize supervisory officials, such as supervisors engaged in mechanics departments of various railroads. The negotiations and Agreements between carrier and labor organization were then subject to the changes requested by the Federated Shop Crafts during the Rules Movement.
  - National Mediation Board. Case No. A-5610., 1958 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    Case between St. Louis Southwestern Rwy and the BLE, BLF&E, and BRT re changing Rules of their Agreement
  - American Railway Supervisors Association: Request for Wage Increase and Certain Changes in the Rules of Their Agreement, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Railway Patrolmen's International Union: Request for Wage Increase and Certain Changes in the Rules of Their Agreement, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Draft Memorandum of Agreement., 1956 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    Between M&St.L Rwy and Railroad Yardmasters of America
  - Memorandum of Agreement Between M&St.L Railway and Railroad Yardmasters of America, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    Includes correspondence and minutes to meetings.
  - Mediation Agreement between Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees and M&St.L Railway [Folder 1 of 2], 1958-1959 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    Includes Mediation Agreement, Case No. A-5987, Western Carrier Conference Circulars, and correspondence
  - Mediation Agreement between Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees and M&St.L Railway [Folder 2 of 2], 1958-1959 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen: Notice of desire to change existing agreements, 1956-1957 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    Circulars 748 series
  - Mechanic Department Supervisors Organizing by American Railway Supervisors Association., 1940-1947 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    Includes internal memos, correspondence, circulars from the National Mediation Board, and Rules and Agreements.
  - Non-Operating Crafts. Proposed Changes to Agreements, Wages and Rules, 1958-1959 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    Section 6 Notices
  - Conductors, Notice of desire to change existing schedule agreements, 1956-1960 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    Filed by the Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen.
  - Firemen and Oilers. Memorandum of Agreement and Claims, 1955-1959 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    Filed by International Brotherhood of Firemen and Oilers
  - National Rules Movement. [Folder 1 of 3]., 1958 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    Section 6 Notice Served: 1. The operation of rules establishing time limits for the handling of claims and grievances; 2. Hiring practices; 3. Safety, health, and sanitation; 4. Accidents.
  - National Rules Movement. [Folder 2 of 3]., 1958 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - National Rules Movement. [Folder 3 of 3]., 1958 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - National Rules Movement. Section 6 Notices. Association of Western Railways, Circular Series 875., 1958 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Chief Operating Officers Quarterly Meeting. Memorandum re Discussion of National Rules Movement., 1959 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    Folder also contains correspondence, circulars, and appendixes to old agreements.
  - New Rule for Working Conditions and Compensation. Circulars 753 Series, in re Section 6 Notices., 1956-1959 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    In handling Western Union business. Filed by Order of Railroad Telegraphers.
  - Master File. Non-Operating Crafts. Circulars Series 901 in re Section 6 Notices., 1959-1960 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    Revision of vacation and holiday agreement between carriers and non-operating crafts.
  - Clerks. Section 6 Notices., 1959 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    Revision of vacation and holiday agreement. Filed by Brotherhood of Railway and Steamship Clerks, Freight Handlers, Express & Station Employees.
  - Clerks. Section 6 Notices., 1959 (Box 6, Folder 35)
    Designation of Western Carriers' Conference as representative for M&St.L Rwy.
  - Non-Operating Crafts. Section 6 Notices. Circulars and Agreement, 1959-1960 (Box 6, Folder 39)
    Contains revised Agreements with non-operating crafts.
  - Yardmaster. Section 6 Notices, 1959-1960 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    Filed by Railroad Yardmasters of America.
  - Yardmaster. Section 6 Notices. Circular Letters. Nos. 856-series, 1957-1959 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Dispatchers. Section 6 Notices., 1957-1960 (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Series X: Minneapolis and St. Louis Railway. Local Agreements, Conferences, and Reports, 1926-1960
  This series contains records of the local agreements the M&St.L had with various railroad labor organizations. Also included are reports of conferences between the local representatives of the labor organizations and the M&St.L representatives. These agreements are interesting because of their focus on smaller and more local concerns that are not always represented in the national agreements. Many of these records are about the M&St.L facility on Fort Dodge, Iowa. Of particular interest are the blue prints for a proposed office building, maps of the train yards, and an attempt by the M&St.L to rent space from the Illinois Central Railroad to defray the costs of maintaining their own facilities.
  Also located in this series is a folder containing articles and essays on the issue of featherbedding. Featherbedding is the practice of hiring more workers than are needed to perform a given job. The term is often used by management to refer to labor union contracts which require them to keep a certain number of staff employed, even in instances in which they are no longer needed, such as with the rise of automated workflows that render certain positions obsolete. Certain local agreements are also filed with theses clippings, presumably because the M&St.L felt that these Agreements were example of the same.
  Of particular interest is a file regarding the use of Edifone Equipment to record formal investigations. It is included in this series because it was a policy adopted by the M&St.L and agreed upon by the various locals. However, the introduction of this equipment is indicative of the effects automation began to have on the work, particularly with regard to the clerks and stenographers employed by the M&St.L.
  - Reports on Conferences between Minneapolis and St. Louis Railway and BLF&E, 1958-1959 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    In re amending agreements to include Ft. Dodge, improve working conditions
  - Minneapolis and Saint Louis Railway. Proposed Office Building. Fort Dodge, Illinois. Blueprints., 1959 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    3 sets of blueprints (oversize)
  - M&St.L Rwy. Mechanical Department. Fort Dodge, Illinois., 1958 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - M&St.L Rwy. Request to rent space from Illinois Central Railroad in Ft. Dodge, 1957-1958 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Report re Conference in re Hostler Exams, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    Between M&St.L Rwy and BLF&E.
  - Report re Conference in re Hostlers and Building a Wye. Watertown, South Dakota., 1959 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Report re Conference in re Hostlers. Cedar Lake, Illinois., 1959 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Report re Conference in re Hostlers. Oklahoma, IA., 1955 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Report re Conference in re Placement of GP Locomotives., 1959 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Cost of operating Fort Dodge, Iowa. Freight Station., 1958 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    Includes correspondence with Illinois Central asking to rent part of their facilities. Contains freight station maps.